Hello everyone, and welcome to a new IBM
i RPG sample video.
This is episode 12 of the series learn
RPG on IBM i with VS code.
In the previous videos, we've learned
how to declare variables, work with
arrays, build data structures, and write
more complex programs.
But until now, every program we've
written
has been completely independent. Real
applications don't work that way.
Programs need to communicate with each
other. They need to send information,
receive information, and sometimes
return results.
The way they do that is through
parameters.
Today, we'll learn how to declare
parameters, how to receive values from
another program, and we'll also look at
some very useful parameter options that
you'll see constantly in professional
RPG code.
So, let's go.
Well, what are parameters? Well, imagine
we have a program that prints customer
information. Instead of hard-coding the
customer number inside the program,
wouldn't it be better if another program
could simply send it?
That's exactly what parameters are. They
allow one program to pass information to
another.
Up until now, all our programs started
like this.
Let me open it.
Okay.
This is the way we are starting all our
programs.
But today, we're going to introduce a
new section.
The new section is this.
Well,
uh the PI stands for procedure
interface.
This defines the parameters that our
program expects to receive.
Well, let's build our first example.
Uh let me write.
Okay.
Well, this is very simple. Notice that
for parameters, we are using annotation
like this. P and the name of the uh
variable variable
uh using camel case, okay?
Uh this way we are we always know that a
variable in our is a parameter in our
code.
Well, our program expects one parameter
that is P customer in this case. The
type is uh character of 10 positions.
And then we are writing hello and the
name of the customer. It is very simple,
okay?
What if we want to uh receive more than
one parameter? Well,
receiver
receiving multiple uh values is just as
easy. Uh
just we only have to add um more
parameters here. Amount, for example.
And
city, for example.
Okay?
Well,
uh well, we here we have three
parameters with three different uh data
types, okay? In this case, we'll need to
call to this program using three
parameters, okay?
Each parameter is received in the same
order. The order is extremely important.
If we swap the parameters, the program
will receive incorrect values. And if
the values are not compatible compatible
with data type, it will crash, okay?
So, this is uh very important.
Well, sometimes a parameter is only used
for reading.
We don't want the called program to not
modify it.
For that, we will use const.
And it is written this way.
const
Okay? And it is written here after the
type.
const tell RPG that this parameter is
read-only.
Or uh you only
uh you also can say that it is an input
parameter, okay?
Inside our program, we can display it as
as in this example. But, we cannot do
something like this.
Okay?
If we do this,
then the compiler will immediately
generate an error.
Using const is considered a good
practice whenever your procedure only
needs to read the parameter.
This is especially useful for for
character strings, large data
structures, or arrays because RPG can
pass them efficiently without creating
unnecessary copies. We'll talk about all
these in future videos, okay?
Well, sometimes a parameter is possible
that is optional.
The caller uh may pass it or may decide
not to.
For that, we use options
uh no pass this way.
For example, we can write
this other uh parameter, CD.
Also const and options
no pass.
Well,
now the second parameter here becomes
optional.
It is important to say that if a
parameter is optional using no pass, as
in this case, then the the of parameters
must uh be also optional. We cannot add
a new parameter
here
this way
and
and do
do it. Okay, we we will get a
compilation error in this case. Okay?
Okay, but how do we know if the program
has received the optional parameter?
Well, for that we
we have two different options. Okay?
So, for that we can use params
this way.
params
that is returning the number of
parameters received. For example, in
this case we can say if params is more
than one
then
we can
send
the customer lives in
for example.
Okay, we can move this here from
here.
Okay, we can do this.
Or the other option, that is my favorite
option, is using past.
In this case, with past we can ask if a
parameter has been received
or not directly.
For example, in this case we can do
something like this if
past
city
P city
then
we will send this message to the job
log. Okay?
Of course, if not
Well, if not we can do whatever
whatever we we need. Okay?
This is a very common technique in
professional RPG programs.
Well, there is another way to make
parameters optional. instead of not
passing the parameter, we
can pass a special value called omit.
For that, our parameter must be declared
as option omit this way. For example, we
can
imagine we
can omit this parameter.
But, the age
is obligatory, okay?
Well, in this case,
we can omit the city, for example. This
way, we can
Well, in this case, we can use
omitted to know if this parameter has
been passed or not. For example,
we can say
right here if
this
and then write
this way.
Okay?
And this program then, if we call to
this program with the first parameter,
that is obligatory, and the second
parameter can be
a call with an omit with this We can
write this in the call, okay?
And the age is obligatory. So, we are
checking here all these things and write
the
the city if it is not omitted.
And the age is written in all the cases.
We'll see in the next videos how useful
is using omit in some cases.
But, notice the difference. With no
pass, the parameter simply wasn't sent.
Okay, past will return false.
With omit, the parameter exists. So, if
you use past,
uh then it will return true.
In these cases, uh you'll need to use
omitted to check if the parameter is
omit or not.
Okay, uh these are two different
concepts.
Okay, now let me create a new program, a
very simple, that will work with two
possible parameters. Okay, let me write
it.
Uh we're going to have customer uh name.
Okay, let let me write it. Customer
name.
This way.
Camel case, remember.
Then customer age.
Let me write it in this type.
This is very sim- more simple.
Then let me remove this, and
let me add here options. No pass to this
parameter. Okay?
And the program will
write
the customer name is plus per P customer
name.
And if past
P customer age,
then
we'll send the message
with
and the customer age
for example. Okay?
Very simple program. Okay?
As you can see, we have uh these two
parameters. The first is obligatory
parameter, and it must be passed by
reference because we are not using here
the const keyword. Okay?
We'll see it later how it works.
Well, now let's create a new different
program that we'll call to this one
using parameters. Of course, you'll see
that if your program does not have
parameters, the call is identical, just
sending no parameters, okay?
Well, let me write uh the other program
with the same structure.
For example,
let me copy this program to another one.
Copy.
Okay.
Let me open it.
And
we're going to have a
structure similar structure, okay?
But in this case, we are going to
declare
this.
I'm going to explain it later.
Okay.
Well, very simple, too.
Well, as you see, uh this is the way
we're going to declare an external
program in our program using this DCLPR.
Okay? Then we are writing that is an
external external program, the library,
the object name. And in this case, uh in
this case, the program is uh PARMS1. I'm
going uh I'm going to to call to this uh
program to PARMS1. And then
uh
they uh
different possible parameters. Okay? As
you see in the declaration, we are not
using name.
We are not using a name. We are using an
a store and an N.
That means no name, okay? You don't need
to add here a name for the parameter.
Okay?
Later, we are declaring a variable, as
you can see here, this customer name.
Uh that will use as the first parameter.
Remember that it is uh if it is not
declared as const, in as in this case,
it must be sent using an a variable.
Okay?
And we are assigning the value uh a
value to our variable here and here,
too. And then we are calling to program
two times, the first time with only one
parameters, and the second time with two
parameters. As you can see, the second
parameter, as it is const, we can uh
send it this way.
And as it is optional, we can uh call uh
with one parameter and with uh two
parameters in this case. Okay?
Well,
let's uh let's see if if the programs
work. Let me compile the first one.
PARMS uh one. Okay, it is compiled
correctly.
And let me compile the second one.
That is also compiled correctly. And
then we are going to run the second one.
So, we are going to open the
this filter that I have uh
prepared.
As you can see, we can set here that we
want to see all the objects named param
asterisk. And when and then we are going
to get all the parameters that start
with params. The
these two one
both of them.
And then we can run it. Run action, call
program.
And as you see,
in the first execution, the customer
name is John. That's correct. And in the
second execution, the customer name is
Mary and the customer is 28. Why it is
bringing this? Well, because we have in
this case
two different parameters. And if the
second parameter this is passed, then we
are writing this second message to the
job log. Okay? So, it is working
correctly.
How about adding const to our first
parameter? Because inside the first
program, it is not changed, so it is not
necessary to send it by reference. So,
we can
add here const. Okay, it is an input
parameter. Okay?
So, we can
compile it this way.
As you can see,
correct.
And then we can add here
const.
We can remove this
this variable. We we are not going to
need it.
And we can
write here directly
John.
Remove this. Remove this. And
uh sorry.
Remove this and then write here Mary.
Okay? Then the program is
more readable, more simple, and it works
in the same way.
We can see
we can run it again.
Run action, call program.
And we are getting the same.
The customer name is John, the customer
name is Mary, and the customer is 28.
So, it works correctly as in the other
way.
Okay?
Well,
I must say that
well, the programs are not completely
correct because we are not using
correctly the activation groups. As you
can see here, we have the activation
group new
and also in the program number one, we
have activation group new. And this is
not correct. But at this moment, it's
not important. We'll talk about ID and
activation groups in the future videos,
okay? So, it doesn't matter.
You can
test these programs this way and it will
run correctly.
Well, before finishing,
here
here are a few recommendations, okay?
When to use const? Well, we are going to
use const whenever the parameter is only
read. This is a very good practice and
we'll use it also when calling
procedures. We'll see it in the next
video.
When to use options no pass? Well,
we will use it when the caller may or
may not provide the parameter.
It's very useful when you have a program
that has
two, three parameters and imagine that
the program is called by thousands of of
different programs or hundreds of
different programs. If you don't
want to change all those calls, you only
have to add a new parameters with
options no pass
and all the calls will
work in the same way. Okay?
When to use pass? Well, we are going to
use pass
before accessing an optional parameter,
okay?
So, if we have as in this uh,
as in this uh, example, if we have a
parameter, in this case, P_CustomerAge,
and it is optional,
the way,
the best way for, uh,
working with it is first
checking if it is passed.
Okay? Because if it is not, if it is not
passed, and we are, uh, writing this
directly,
we will get a crash. Well, when to use
options omit? Well, you'll use option
omit when you want to the caller
uh,
to explicitly, explicitly indicate that
the parameter has been omitted. Okay?
Following all these simple rules will
make your programs much more flexible
and easier to reuse.
Well, so we in this video we learned how
RPG programs receive information using
parameters, how to declare them with
DCL-PI, and how to make our programs
more flexible using const, option no
pass, options omit.
In the next video, we'll start working
with procedures, and using parameters is
one of the important things for using
procedures, and that's,
uh, why we have talked about them today.
I hope you liked the video and that it
was useful to you. As always, remember
to like and subscribe if you haven't
already. See you on the next video and
thanks for watching.